I'm going to speak to you about the global refugee crisis
سأتحدث إليكم عن أزمة اللاجئين العالمية
and my aim is to show you that this crisis
وهدفي أن أريكم أن هذه الأزمة
is manageable, not unsolvable,
قابلة للإدارة وأنها ليست بلا حل،
but also show you that this is as much about us and who we are
لكن أيضًا أن أريكم أن هذا الأمر يعنينا نحن ومن نكون
as it is a trial of the refugees on the front line.
كما يعني ذلك امتحاناً لللاجئين على الحدود.
For me, this is not just a professional obligation,
بالنسبة لي، ليس هذا تكليفًا مهنيًا فحسب،
because I run an NGO supporting refugees and displaced people around the world.
لأنني أدير منظمة غير حكومية تدعم اللاجئين والنازحين في أنحاء العالم.
It's personal.
فالأمر شخصي بالنسبة لي.
I love this picture.
أحب هذه الصورة.
That really handsome guy on the right,
ذاك الشخص الوسيم جداً على اليمين،
that's not me.
لستُ أنا.
That's my dad, Ralph, in London, in 1940
هذا أبي، رالف، في لندن، سنة 1940
with his father Samuel.
مع أبيه صامويل.
They were Jewish refugees from Belgium.
كانا لاجئين يهوديين من بلجيكا.
They fled the day the Nazis invaded.
فروا يوم احتل النازيون الأرض.
And I love this picture, too.
وأحب هذه الصورة أيضًا.
It's a group of refugee children
هذه مجموعة من الأطفال اللاجئين
arriving in England in 1946 from Poland.
الذين وصلوا إلى بريطانيا سنة 1946 من بولندا.
And in the middle is my mother, Marion.
وفي الوسط، أمي ماريون.
She was sent to start a new life
أرسلت لتبدأ حياة جديدة
in a new country
في بلد جديد
on her own
بمفردها
at the age of 12.
في سن 12.
I know this:
أعلم هذا جيدًا:
if Britain had not admitted refugees
إن لم تكن بريطانيا قد سمحت بدخول اللاجئين
in the 1940s,
في الأربعينيات،
I certainly would not be here today.
لما كنت هنا اليوم بالتأكيد.
Yet 70 years on, the wheel has come full circle.
لكن، بعد 70 سنة، دارت الدائرة.
The sound is of walls being built,
نسمع صوت الجدران وهي تُبنى،
vengeful political rhetoric,
وخطابات سياسية حانقة،
humanitarian values and principles on fire
والقيم والمبادئ الإنسانية تحترق
in the very countries that 70 years ago said never again
في نفس تلك البلدان التي تعهدت قبل 70 سنة
to statelessness and hopelessness for the victims of war.
بألا تهجير ولا فقدان للأمل لضحايا الحرب.
Last year, every minute,
في السنة الماضية، في كل دقيقة
24 more people were displaced from their homes
نزح 24 شخص من ديارهم
by conflict, violence and persecution:
بسبب صراع أو عنف أو اضطهاد:
another chemical weapon attack in Syria,
هجوم آخر بالأسلحة الكيماوية في سوريا،
the Taliban on the rampage in Afghanistan,
هيجان طالبان في أفغانستان،
girls driven from their school in northeast Nigeria by Boko Haram.
اختطاف فتيات من مدارسهن شمال نيجيريا من طرف بوكو حرام.
These are not people moving to another country
هؤلاء ليسوا أشخاصًا رحلوا إلى بلد آخر
to get a better life.
ليحظوا بحياة كريمة.
They're fleeing for their lives.
لقد فروا بحياتهم.
It's a real tragedy
وإنها لمأساة حقيقية
that the world's most famous refugee can't come to speak to you here today.
ألا يتمكن أشهر لاجئ في العالم من التحدث إليكم اليوم.
Many of you will know this picture.
العديد منكم يعرفون هذه الصورة.
It shows the lifeless body
فهي تري جسدًا بلا حياة
of five-year-old Alan Kurdi,
لآلان الكردي ذي الخمس سنوات،
a Syrian refugee who died in the Mediterranean in 2015.
وهو لاجئ سوري لفظ أنفاسه الأخيرة في البحر الأبيض المتوسط سنة 2015.
He died alongside 3,700 others trying to get to Europe.
توفي إلى جانب 3700 آخرين ممن كانوا يحاولون الوصول إلى أوروبا.
The next year, 2016,
في السنة التي تلتها، 2016
5,000 people died.
توفي 5000 شخص.
It's too late for them,
فات الأوان بالنسبة لهم،
but it's not too late for millions of others.
لكنه لم يفت بالنسبة لملايين آخرين.
It's not too late for people like Frederick.
لم يفت الأوان بالنسبة لأشخاص مثل فريديريك.
I met him in the Nyarugusu refugee camp in Tanzania.
التقيته في مخيم نياروغوسو للاجئين في تنزانيا.
He's from Burundi.
جاء من بوروندي.
He wanted to know where could he complete his studies.
أراد أن يعرف أين يمكنه أن يكمل دراسته.
He'd done 11 years of schooling. He wanted a 12th year.
أتم 11 سنة في المدرسة، ويريد أن يكمل عامه 12.
He said to me, "I pray that my days do not end here
قال لي،" أدعو ألا تنتهي أيامي هنا
in this refugee camp."
في مخيم اللاجئين هذا."
And it's not too late for Halud.
ولم يفت الأوان بالنسبة لخلود.
Her parents were Palestinian refugees
كان والداها لاجئين فلسطينين
living in the Yarmouk refugee camp outside Damascus.
يعيشان في مخيم اليرموك للاجئين خارج دمشق.
She was born to refugee parents,
ولدت لأبوين لاجئين،
and now she's a refugee herself in Lebanon.
وهي نفسها الآن لاجئة في لبنان.
She's working for the International Rescue Committee to help other refugees,
وهي تعمل في منظمة الإنقاذ الدولية لمساعدة اللاجئين الآخرين،
but she has no certainty at all
لكنها لا تملك أي ضمانات
about her future,
حيال مستقبلها،
where it is or what it holds.
أين هو أو ماذا يحمل لها.
This talk is about Frederick, about Halud
هذه المحادثة عن فريديريك، عن خلود
and about millions like them:
وعن ملايين آخرين مثلهم:
why they're displaced,
لماذا تم تهجيرهم،
how they survive, what help they need and what our responsibilities are.
كيف يعيشون، ما المساعدة التي يحتاجونها، وما هي مسؤووليتنا.
I truly believe this,
أؤمن حقاً بهذا،
that the biggest question in the 21st century
أن السؤال الأكبر في القرن 21
concerns our duty to strangers.
يتعلق بواجبنا تجاه الغرباء.
The future "you" is about your duties
أنت في المستقبل، هو عن واجباتك
to strangers.
تجاه الغرباء.
You know better than anyone,
تعرفون أكثر من غيركم،
the world is more connected than ever before,
أن العالم أكثر تواصلاً من أي وقت مضى،
yet the great danger
لكن الخطر الأكبر
is that we're consumed by our divisions.
أننا نغوص في انقساماتنا.
And there is no better test of that
ولا يوجد أي امتحان أفضل لهذا
than how we treat refugees.
من كيفية تعاملنا مع اللاجئين.
Here are the facts: 65 million people
إليكم الوقائع: 65 مليون شخص
displaced from their homes by violence and persecution last year.
نزحوا من منازلهم بسبب العنف والاضطهاد في السنة الماضية.
If it was a country,
إن كان هذا بلدًا،
that would be the 21st largest country in the world.
فسيحتل المرتبة 21 من بين البلدان الأكثر تعدادً للسكان.
Most of those people, about 40 million, stay within their own home country,
أغلب هؤلاء الناس، حوالي 40 مليون، يظلون في أوطانهم،
but 25 million are refugees.
لكن 25 مليون منهم هم لاجئون.
That means they cross a border into a neighboring state.
هذا يعني أنهم يعبرون الحدود في اتجاه بلد جار.
Most of them are living in poor countries,
أغلبهم يعيشون في دول فقيرة،
relatively poor or lower-middle-income countries, like Lebanon,
دول فقيرة نسبيًا أو ذات دخل متوسط أو ضعيف مثل لبنان،
where Halud is living.
حيث تعيش خلود.
In Lebanon, one in four people is a refugee,
في لبنان، واحد من أربعة أشخاص يعد لاجئًا،
a quarter of the whole population.
ما يمثل ربع تعداد السكان.
And refugees stay for a long time.
ويبقى اللاجئون هناك وقتًا طويلًا.
The average length of displacement
متوسط مدة النزوح
is 10 years.
تصل إلى 10 سنوات.
I went to what was the world's largest refugee camp, in eastern Kenya.
ذهبت إلى حيث كان أكبر مخيم لللاجئين في العالم، في شرق كينيا.
It's called Dadaab.
ويدعى داداب.
It was built in 1991-92
وقد بني سنة 1991-92
as a "temporary camp" for Somalis fleeing the civil war.
ك"مخيم مؤقت" للصوماليين الفارين من الحرب الأهلية.
I met Silo.
التقيت سيلو.
And naïvely I said to Silo,
وقلت لسيلو بكل سذاجة،
"Do you think you'll ever go home to Somalia?"
"هل تظنين أنك ستعودين إلى الديار، في الصومال يومًا؟"
And she said, "What do you mean, go home?
فقالت، "ماذا تقصد بالعودة للديار؟
I was born here."
لقد وُلدتُ هنا."
And then when I asked the camp management
وبعدها حين سألت إدارة المخيم
how many of the 330,000 people in that camp were born there,
كم شخصا من بين 330000 شخص في المخيم ولدوا هناك،
they gave me the answer:
أعطوني الجواب:
100,000.
100000.
That's what long-term displacement means.
هذا ما يعنيه النزوح طويل المدى.
Now, the causes of this are deep:
الآن، أسباب هذا الأمر عميقة:
weak states that can't support their own people,
الدول الضعيفة التي لا تقوى على إعالة مواطنيها،
an international political system
نظام سياسي عالمي
weaker than at any time since 1945
أضعف ما يكون منذ سنة 1945
and differences over theology, governance, engagement with the outside world
وانقسامات بشأن المعتقدات والحكامة والانخراط مع العالم الخارجي
in significant parts of the Muslim world.
في مناطق مهمة من العالم الإسلامي.
Now, those are long-term, generational challenges.
الآن هذه تحديات جيلية بعيدة المدى.
That's why I say that this refugee crisis is a trend and not a blip.
لذلك فأنا أقول أن أزمة اللاجئين هي ظاهرة وليست نقطة ضباب.
And it's complex, and when you have big, large, long-term, complex problems,
وهي معقدة، وحين تكون لديك مشاكل معقدة وكبيرة وضخمة وطويلة المدى،
people think nothing can be done.
يعتقد الناس أنها ميؤوس منها.
When Pope Francis went to Lampedusa,
عندما ذهب البابا فرانسيس إلى لامبدوزا،
off the coast of Italy, in 2014,
على الساحل الإيطالي، سنة 2014،
he accused all of us and the global population
اتهمنا جميعًا والعالم جميعًا
of what he called "the globalization of indifference."
بما أسماه "عولمة اللامبالاة."
It's a haunting phrase.
إنها جملة مميتة.
It means that our hearts have turned to stone.
تعني أن قلوبنا تحولت إلى حجر.
Now, I don't know, you tell me.
الآن، لست أدري، أخبروني أنتم.
Are you allowed to argue with the Pope, even at a TED conference?
هل من المسموح لكم أن تتجادلوا مع البابا حتى وإن كنتم في مؤتمر TED؟
But I think it's not right.
لكن أعتقد أن هذا ليس صائبًا.
I think people do want to make a difference,
أعتقد أن الناس يريدون أن يحدثوا فرقًا،
but they just don't know whether there are any solutions to this crisis.
لكنهم فقط لا يعلمون إن كانت هناك أي حلول للأزمة.
And what I want to tell you today
وما أريد أن أقوله لكم اليوم
is that though the problems are real, the solutions are real, too.
أنه رغم أن المشاكل حقيقية، فإن الحلول حقيقية أيضًا.
Solution one:
الحل الأول:
these refugees need to get into work in the countries where they're living,
يحتاج هؤلاء اللاجئين أن يعملوا في البلدان التي يعيشون فيها،
and the countries where they're living need massive economic support.
والبلدان التي يعيشون فيها تحتاج دعمًا اقتصاديًا ضخمًا.
In Uganda in 2014, they did a study:
في أوغندا سنة 2014، قاموا بدراسة:
80 percent of refugees in the capital city Kampala
80 في المئة من اللاجئين في العاصمة كامبالا
needed no humanitarian aid because they were working.
لا يحتاجون أي مساعدات إنسانية لأنهم كانوا يعملون.
They were supported into work.
كان يتم دعمهم في العمل.
Solution number two:
الحل الثاني:
education for kids is a lifeline, not a luxury,
تعليم الأطفال هو حق حياتي وليس رفاهية،
when you're displaced for so long.
حين يتم تهجيرك لمدة طويلة.
Kids can bounce back when they're given the proper social, emotional support
يمكن للأطفال أن يقفوا على أرجلهم حين يتلقون الدعم الاجتماعي والعاطفي الملائم
alongside literacy and numeracy.
إلى جانب تعلم القراءة والحساب.
I've seen it for myself.
رأيت ذلك بنفسي.
But half of the world's refugee children of primary school age
لكن نصف الأطفال اللاجئين في العالم ممن هم في سن التعليم الإبتدائي
get no education at all,
لايتلقون أي تعليم إطلاقًا،
and three-quarters of secondary school age get no education at all.
وثلاثة أرباع من هم في سن التعليم الثانوي لا يتلقون أي تعليم إطلاقًا.
That's crazy.
هذا جنون.
Solution number three:
الحل الثالث:
most refugees are in urban areas, in cities, not in camps.
يتواجد معظم اللاجئين في المناطق الحضرية، في المدن، وليس في المخيمات.
What would you or I want if we were a refugee in a city?
ما الذي كنت سأريده أنا أو أنت لو كنا لاجئين في المدن؟
We would want money to pay rent or buy clothes.
سنريد مالًا لندفع الإيجار ولنشتري الملابس.
That is the future of the humanitarian system,
هذا هو مستقبل نظام المساعدات الإنسانية،
or a significant part of it:
أو جزء مهم منه:
give people cash so that you boost the power of refugees
اعطوا الناس النقود لكي تتمكنوا من دعم قوة اللاجئين
and you'll help the local economy.
وستساعدون الاقتصاد المحلي.
And there's a fourth solution, too,
وهناك حل رابع أيضًا،
that's controversial but needs to be talked about.
هذا محل خلاف، لكنه يستحق أن نتحدث عنه.
The most vulnerable refugees need to be given a new start
معظم اللاجئين الضعفاء يحتاجون بداية جديدة
and a new life in a new country,
وحياة جديدة في بلد جديد،
including in the West.
بما في ذلك الغرب.
The numbers are relatively small, hundreds of thousands, not millions,
الأرقام صغيرة نسبيًا، بضعة مئات من الآلاف، وليس ملايين،
but the symbolism is huge.
لكن الرمزية كبيرة جدًا.
Now is not the time to be banning refugees,
ليس الوقت مناسباً الآن لمقاطعة اللاجئين،
as the Trump administration proposes.
كما تقترح إدارة ترامب.
It's a time to be embracing people who are victims of terror.
بل إنه الوقت لاحتضان ضحايا الإرهاب.
And remember --
وتذكروا --
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Remember, anyone who asks you, "Are they properly vetted?"
تذكروا، كل من يسألكم، " هل تم تمحيصهم بشكل جيد؟"
that's a really sensible and good question to ask.
هذا سؤال حساس وجيد لأن يطرح.
The truth is, refugees arriving for resettlement
الحقيقة أن اللاجئين الذين جاؤوا من أجل إعادة الإدماج
are more vetted than any other population arriving in our countries.
هم أكثر تمحيصاً من أي مجموعة أخرى قدمت إلى بلداننا.
So while it's reasonable to ask the question,
في حين أنه من المناسب طرح السؤال،
it's not reasonable to say that refugee is another word for terrorist.
ليس من المناسب أن نجعل كلمة لاجئ مرادفةً لإرهابي.
Now, what happens --
الآن، ما يحصل --
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
What happens when refugees can't get work,
ما يحصل حين لا يجد اللاجئون عملًا،
they can't get their kids into school,
لايستطيعون إدخال أولادهم إلى المدرسة،
they can't get cash, they can't get a legal route to hope?
لا يحصلون على النقود، لايحصلون على طريقة قانونية للأمل؟
What happens is they take risky journeys.
ما يحصل أنهم يسلكون مسارات خطرة.
I went to Lesbos, this beautiful Greek island, two years ago.
منذ سنتين ذهبت إلى ليسبوس، هذه الجزيرة اليونانية الجميلة،
It's a home to 90,000 people.
حيث يسكن 90000 شخص.
In one year, 500,000 refugees went across the island.
في غضون عام، عبر 500000 لاجئ الجزيرة.
And I want to show you what I saw
وأريد أن أريكم ماذا رأيت
when I drove across to the north of the island:
حين كنت أسير بالسيارة شمال الجزيرة:
a pile of life jackets of those who had made it to shore.
كومة من سترات النجاة التي خلفها من تمكنوا من الوصول إلى الشاطئ.
And when I looked closer,
وحين نظرت عن قرب،
there were small life jackets for children,
كانت هناك سترات نجاة للأطفال،
yellow ones.
صفراء اللون.
And I took this picture.
والتقطت هده الصورة.
You probably can't see the writing, but I want to read it for you.
قد لا يمكنكم رؤية الكتابة لكنني أود أن أقرأها لكم.
"Warning: will not protect against drowning."
" تحذير: لا تحمي هذه السترة من الغرق."
So in the 21st century,
إذن في القرن 21،
children are being given life jackets
يُعطى الأطفال سترات نجاة
to reach safety in Europe
لكي يصلوا إلى أوروبا
even though those jackets will not save their lives
رغم أن هذه السترات لن تنقذ حياتهم
if they fall out of the boat that is taking them there.
إذا ما سقطوا من على القارب الذي يقلهم إلى هناك.
This is not just a crisis, it's a test.
هذه ليست أزمة، بل امتحان.
It's a test that civilizations have faced down the ages.
امتحان واجهته الحضارات منذ عصور.
It's a test of our humanity.
امتحان لإنسانيتنا.
It's a test of us in the Western world
امتحان لنا نحن في العالم الغربي
of who we are and what we stand for.
لهويتنا ومبادئنا.
It's a test of our character, not just our policies.
امتحان لشخصيتنا، ليس فقط لسياساتنا.
And refugees are a hard case.
واللاجئون قضية صعبة.
They do come from faraway parts of the world.
فهم بأتون من أجزاء بعيدة من العالم.
They have been through trauma.
مروا بالصدمة.
They're often of a different religion.
هم غالباً من ديانة مختلفة.
Those are precisely the reasons we should be helping refugees,
وهذه بالضبط هي الأسباب التي علينا أن نساعد اللاجئين من أجلها،
not a reason not to help them.
وليست سبب عدم مساعدتنا إياهم.
And it's a reason to help them because of what it says about us.
وهذا سبب لأن نساعدهم، لما يقوله هذا عنا.
It's revealing of our values.
فهذا يكشف قيمنا.
Empathy and altruism are two of the foundations of civilization.
التعاطف والإيثار ركيزتان من ركائز الحضارة.
Turn that empathy and altruism into action
فلنحول التعاطف والإيثار إلى أفعال
and we live out a basic moral credo.
وسنعيش العقيدة الإنسانية الأساسية.
And in the modern world, we have no excuse.
وفي العالم المتحضر، ليست لنا أية حجة.
We can't say we don't know what's happening in Juba, South Sudan,
لايمكننا أن نقول بأننا لا نعلم مايجري في جوبا، جنوب السودان،
or Aleppo, Syria.
أو في حلب في سوريا.
It's there, in our smartphone
إنها هنا، في هواتفنا الذكية
in our hand.
في أيدينا.
Ignorance is no excuse at all.
الجهل لم يعد حجة على الإطلاق.
Fail to help, and we show we have no moral compass at all.
إن لم نقدم المساعدة، سيتببن أننا لا نمتلك بوصلة أخلاقية إطلاقًا.
It's also revealing about whether we know our own history.
سيكشف هذا أيضاً ما إذا كنا نعرف تاريخنا أو نجهله.
The reason that refugees have rights around the world
السبب في امتلاك اللاجئين حقوقًا حول العالم
is because of extraordinary Western leadership
راجع إلى القيادة الغربية الاستثنائية
by statesmen and women after the Second World War
من خلال رجال ونساء الدولة بعد الحرب العالمية الثانية
that became universal rights.
حيث أصبحت حقوقًا عالمية.
Trash the protections of refugees, and we trash our own history.
إذا مارمينا حماية اللاجئين بعيدًا، سنرمي تاريخنا أيضًا.
This is --
هذا --
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
This is also revealing about the power of democracy
هذا يكشف أيضًا عن قوة الديمقراطية
as a refuge from dictatorship.
كملاذ من الديكتاتورية.
How many politicians have you heard say,
كم من السياسيين سمعتموهم يقولون،
"We believe in the power of our example, not the example of our power."
"نؤمن بقوة نموذجنا وليس في نموذج قوتنا."
What they mean is what we stand for is more important than the bombs we drop.
ما يقصدونه هو أن مبادئنا هي أهم من القنابل التي نرميها.
Refugees seeking sanctuary
اللاجئون الباحثون عن الأمان
have seen the West as a source of hope and a place of haven.
رؤوا في الغرب مصدراً للأمل وملاذاً.
Russians, Iranians,
روسيون، إيرانيون،
Chinese, Eritreans, Cubans,
صينيون، إيريتيريون، كوبيون،
they've come to the West for safety.
جاؤوا إلى الغرب من أجل الأمان.
We throw that away at our peril.
نرمي كل هذا بعيدًا فنتحمل النتائج.
And there's one other thing it reveals about us:
وهناك أيضًا شيء آخر يكشفه هذا عنا:
whether we have any humility for our own mistakes.
إن كنا نمتلك أي تواضع لنتقبل أخطائنا.
I'm not one of these people
لست واحداً من أولئك الناس
who believes that all the problems in the world are caused by the West.
الذين يؤمنون أن كل المشاكل في العالم هي بسبب الغرب.
They're not.
هي ليست كذلك.
But when we make mistakes, we should recognize it.
لكن حين نرتكب أخطاءً، علينا أن نعترف بها.
It's not an accident that the country which has taken
ليس من الصدفة أن البلد الذي أخذ
more refugees than any other, the United States,
أكبر عدد من اللاجئين أكثر من غيره، أمريكا،
has taken more refugees from Vietnam than any other country.
حيث أخذت الكثير من اللاجئين من فيتنام أكثر من أي بلد أخر.
It speaks to the history.
هذا يعني الكثير للتاريخ.
But there's more recent history, in Iraq and Afghanistan.
لكن هناك تاريخ أقرب في العراق وأفغانستان.
You can't make up for foreign policy errors
لا يمكن أن تصحح أخطاء السياسة الخارجية
by humanitarian action,
بأفعال إنسانية،
but when you break something, you have a duty to try to help repair it,
لكن حين تكسر شيئاً ما، فمن واجبك أن تساعد في إصلاحه،
and that's our duty now.
وهذا هو واجبنا الآن.
Do you remember at the beginning of the talk,
هل تذكرون في بداية المحادثة،
I said I wanted to explain that the refugee crisis
قلت أنني أريد أن أشرح أن أزمة اللاجئين
was manageable, not insoluble?
قابلة للإدارة وأنها ليست بلا حل؟
That's true. I want you to think in a new way,
هذا صحيح، أريدكم أن تفكروا بطريقة جديدة،
but I also want you to do things.
لكنني أريدكم أن تقوموا بأشياء فعلية.
If you're an employer,
لو كنت رب عمل،
hire refugees.
شغِّل لاجئين.
If you're persuaded by the arguments,
لو كنت تحب النقاش
take on the myths
صحح الخرافات
when family or friends or workmates repeat them.
حين يكررها أصدقاؤك أو عائلتك أو زملاؤك.
If you've got money, give it to charities
إن كنت تمتلك المال، اعطِ للمؤسسات الخيرية
that make a difference for refugees around the world.
التي تحدث الفرق في حياة اللاجئين حول العالم.
If you're a citizen,
إن كنت مواطنا،
vote for politicians
صوت لصالح السياسيين
who will put into practice the solutions that I've talked about.
الذين سيضعون حيز التنفيذ الحلول التي تحدثتُ عنها.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
The duty to strangers
الواجب تجاه الغرباء
shows itself
يظهر في حد ذاته
in small ways and big,
بطرق كبيرة أو صغيرة
prosaic and heroic.
البطولة والابتذال.
In 1942,
سنة 1942،
my aunt and my grandmother were living in Brussels
كانت تعيش عمتي وجدتي في بروكسل
under German occupation.
تحت الاحتلال الألماني.
They received a summons
استلما استدعاءً
from the Nazi authorities to go to Brussels Railway Station.
من السلطات النازية بالذهاب إلى محطة القطارات في بروكسل.
My grandmother immediately thought something was amiss.
فطِنت جدتي مباشرة أن هناك خطبًا ما.
She pleaded with her relatives
ترجت أقاريها
not to go to Brussels Railway Station.
ألا يذهبوا إلى محطة القطارات.
Her relatives said to her,
قال لها أقاربها،
"If we don't go, if we don't do what we're told,
"إلم نذهب، إلم نفعل ما قيل لنا
then we're going to be in trouble."
فسنقع في مشاكل كبيرة."
You can guess what happened
يمكنم أن تخمنوا ما حدث
to the relatives who went to Brussels Railway Station.
للأقارب الذين ذهبوا إلى محطة بروكسل للقطارات.
They were never seen again.
لم يعودوا أبدًا.
But my grandmother and my aunt,
لكن جدتي وعمتي
they went to a small village
ذهبتا إلى قرية صغيرة
south of Brussels
جنوب بروكسل
where they'd been on holiday in the decade before,
زارتاها قبل عقد من الزمن، في عطلة،
and they presented themselves at the house of the local farmer,
وقدمتا نفسيهما في بيت مزارع محلي،
a Catholic farmer called Monsieur Maurice,
مزارع كاثوليكي اسمه السيد موريس،
and they asked him to take them in.
وطلبتا منه أن يسمح لهما بالدخول.
And he did,
وقد فعل،
and by the end of the war,
ومع نهاية الحرب،
17 Jews, I was told, were living in that village.
قيل لي أن 17 يهودياً كانوا يعيشون في تلك القرية.
And when I was teenager, I asked my aunt,
وحين كنت مراهقاً، سألت عمتي،
"Can you take me to meet Monsieur Maurice?"
"هل يمكنك أن تأخذيني لألتقي السيد موريس؟"
And she said, "Yeah, I can. He's still alive. Let's go and see him."
فقالت، "نعم، أستطيع ذلك، لايزال على قيد الحياة، لنذهب ونزره."
And so, it must have been '83, '84,
إذاً، ربما كانت سنة 83 أو 84،
we went to see him.
ذهبنا لنزوره.
And I suppose, like only a teenager could,
ويمكنني أن أفترض، كأي مراهق،
when I met him,
حينما التقيته،
he was this white-haired gentleman,
كان رجلا ذا شعر أبيض،
I said to him,
فقلت له،
"Why did you do it?
"لم قمت بذلك؟"
Why did you take that risk?"
"لم خاطرت؟"
And he looked at me and he shrugged,
نظر إلي وهز كتفيه،
and he said, in French,
وقال بالفرنسية:
"On doit."
".On doit"
"One must."
"يجب علينا ذلك"
It was innate in him.
كان ذلك فطريا بداخله.
It was natural.
كان طبيعيا.
And my point to you is it should be natural and innate in us, too.
وما أريد إيصاله لكم، أنه يجب أن يكون هذا فطريا وطبيعيا فينا أيضا.
Tell yourself,
قل لنفسك،
this refugee crisis is manageable,
أن أزمة اللاجئين هذه قابلة للإدارة،
not unsolvable,
ليست بلا حل،
and each one of us
وكل واحد منا
has a personal responsibility to help make it so.
لديه مسؤولية فردية ليجعلها كذلك.
Because this is about the rescue of us and our values
لأن هذا متعلق بإنقاذنا نحن وإنقاذ قيمنا
as well as the rescue of refugees and their lives.
كما هو الشأن بالنسبة لإنقاذ اللاجئين وإنقاذ حياتهم.
Thank you very much indeed.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Bruno Giussani: David, thank you. David Miliband: Thank you.
برونو جيوسياني: ديفيد، شكرا لك. ديفيد ميليباند: شكرا لك.
BG: Those are strong suggestions
ب.ج: هذه اقتراحات قوية
and your call for individual responsibility is very strong as well,
ونداؤك من أجل المسؤولية الفردية قوي أيضًا،
but I'm troubled by one thought, and it's this:
لكنني قلق بشأن فكرة واحدة، وهاهي ذي:
you mentioned, and these are your words, "extraordinary Western leadership"
ذكرت، وهذه عباراتك، " قيادة غربية استثنائية"
which led 60-something years ago
والتي أدت خلال 60 سنة ونيف الماضية
to the whole discussion about human rights,
إلى كل هذا النقاش حول حقوق الإنسان،
to the conventions on refugees, etc. etc.
إلى اتفاقيات اللاجئين،و ما إلى ذلك.
That leadership happened after a big trauma
تلك القيادة جاءت بعد صدمة كبيرة
and happened in a consensual political space,
حدثت في فضاء سياسي توافقي،
and now we are in a divisive political space.
ونحن الآن في فضاء سياسي منقسم.
Actually, refugees have become one of the divisive issues.
في الواقع، أصبح اللاجئون أحد هذه القضايا التي أدت للانقسام.
So where will leadership come from today?
إذن من أين ستتدخل القيادة اليوم؟
DM: Well, I think that you're right to say
د.م: حسنًا، أعتقد أنك محق في قولك
that the leadership forged in war
أن القيادة التي تمت صياغتها في الحرب
has a different temper and a different tempo
كانت تتحلى بمزاج مختلف، كانت لها نبرة صوت مختلفة
and a different outlook
كانت لها نظرة مختلفة
than leadership forged in peace.
عن القيادة التي تمت صياغتها في السلم.
And so my answer would be the leadership has got to come from below,
لذا فجوابي سيكون أن على القيادة أن تأتي من الأسفل
not from above.
وليس من الأعلى.
I mean, a recurring theme of the conference this week
أعني، أحد المواضيع التي تم التطرق إليها في المؤتمر هذا الأسبوع
has been about the democratization of power.
هو عن دمقرطة السلطة.
And we've got to preserve our own democracies,
وعلينا أن نحافظ على ديمقراطياتنا،
but we've got to also activate our own democracies.
لكن علينا أيضا أن ننشط ديمقراطياتنا.
And when people say to me,
فحين يحدثني الناس،
"There's a backlash against refugees,"
"أن هناك صراعًا ضد اللاجئين،"
what I say to them is,
ما أقول لهم هو،
"No, there's a polarization,
"لا، هناك استقطاب،
and at the moment,
وفي الوقت الراهن،
those who are fearful are making more noise
يحدث الخائفون ضجيجًا أكثر
than those who are proud."
من أولئك الفخورين."
And so my answer to your question is that we will sponsor and encourage
لذا فإن جوابي عن سؤالك هو أننا سندعم ونشجع
and give confidence to leadership
ونعطي الثقة للقيادة
when we mobilize ourselves.
ونحرك أنفسنا.
And I think that when you are in a position of looking for leadership,
وأعتقد أنه حينما تكون في منصب بحث عن القيادة،
you have to look inside
عليك أن تنظر إلى الداخل
and mobilize in your own community
وأن تحرك مجتمعك
to try to create conditions for a different kind of settlement.
وأن تخلق ظروفًا لنوع آخر من الاستقرار.
BG: Thank you, David. Thanks for coming to TED.
ب.ج: شكرا لك، ديفيد. شكرا لمجيئك لTED.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)